Register of the Payson J. Treat Papers, 1855-1973
Hoover Institution Archives
Payson J. Treat Papers,
1855-1973
60003
Treat, Payson Jackson, 1879-
65 manuscript boxes, 7 envelopes, 1 album box, 1 oversize folder, 4 scrolls, 6 hair pins, 1 utensil 28.7 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, interviews, copies of diplomatic records, speeches, writings, notes, photographs, maps, memorabilia, and printed matter, relating to the diplomatic history of Japan, China, and other countries of the Far East. Includes a pamphlet collection on World War I
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1960.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
China; China--Foreign relations; East Asia; East Asia--Foreign relations; Japan; Japan--Foreign relations
Biographical Note
Payson J. Treat 1879-1972
1879, November 12 Born, New York City, New York
1903 A.B. Wesleyan University.
1903 A.M., Columbia University.
1905-45 Instructor and Professor, Stanford University.
1910 Ph.D., Stanford University.
1910 Author, The National Land System, 1785-1820.
1917 Author, Early Diplomatic Relations Between the United States and Japan, 1853-1865.
1921 Author, Japan and the United States, 1853-1921.
Series Description
- Correspondence File, 1898-1970. (Box Box No. 1 -38.)
  Correspondence with colleagues, friends, and family, including Ephraim D. Adams, Herbert C. Hoover, Stanley K. Hornbeck, Yamoto Ichihashi, David Starr Jordan, Thomas F. Millard, Willys Peck, E.B. Treat (father), and others, arranged chronologically.
- Speeches and Writings, 1905-1968. (Box Box No. 38 -40.)
  Speeches, articles, book reviews, classroom lectures and lecture notes, and clippings, arranged as listed.
- Subject File, 1865-1973. (Box Box No. 41 -51.)
  Correspondence, reports, memoranda, lists, interviews, maps, clippings, and printed matter, arranged alphabetically by subject.
- Research File, 1855-1939. (Box Box No. 51 -59.)
  Manuscripts, reports, correspondence, notes, copies of diplomatic records, and other research materials, which P.J. Treat either acquired from private sources or copied from holdings at the Library of Congress and the National Archives. Arranged alphabetically by the source of the material.
- Pamphlets and Printed Matter, 1914-1923. (Box Box No. 60 -63.)
  Pamphlets and other printed matter relating to World War I, arranged alphabetically by author or title.
- Increment, February, 1985. (Box Box No. 63.)
  Mimeographed correspondence, book reviews, and ethnological studies of the Philippines, 1910-1912, by Otley C. Beyer; and a mimeographed transcript of a speech by D. R. Williams, 1926, relating to legal protection of Americans residing in China
Container List
- Correspondence File, 1898-1970.
  - 1907-12, Letters sent. (Box 1.)
  - 1910-12, Letters received, A-Z.
  - 1913, Letters sent.
  - 1913, Letters received, A-F.
  - 1913, Letters received, G-Z. (Box 2.)
  - 1914-15, Letters sent.
  - 1914-15, Letters received, A-M.
  - 1914-15, Letters received, N-A. (Box 3.)
  - 1916, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1916-17, Correspondence, miscellaneous. (Box 4.)
  - 1916-17, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1918, Correspondence, A-D.
  - 1918, Correspondence, E-Z. (Box 5.)
  - 1919-20, Letters sent.
  - 1919-20, Letters received, A-F.
  - 1919-20, Letters received, G-Z. (Box 6.)
  - 1921, Letters sent.
  - 1921, Letters received while in China.
  - 1921, Letters received, A-M.
  - 1921, Letters received, N-Z. (Box 7.)
  - 1922-23, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1923-24, Correspondence, A-G.
  - 1923-24, Correspondence, H-Z. (Box 8.)
  - 1925, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1926, Correspondence, A-Z. (Box 9.)
  - 1927, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1928 (January-September), Correspondence, miscellaneous. (Box 10.)
  - 1928 (January-September), Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1928 (October) -1929 (June), Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1929 (July-December), Correspondence, A-Z. (Box 11.)
  - 1930, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1930, Correspondence, A-M.
  - 1930, Correspondence, N-Z. (Box 12.)
  - 1931, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1931, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1932, Correspondence, A-F.
  - 1932, Correspondence, G-Z. (Box 13.)
  - 1933, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1934, Correspondence, A-Z. (Box 14.)
  - 1935, Correspondence, A-M.
  - 1935, Correspondence, N-Z. (Box 15.)
  - 1936, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1937, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1937, Correspondence, A-Z (Box 16.)
  - 1938, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1938, Correspondence, A-M.
  - 1938, Correspondence, A-Z. (Box 17.)
  - 1939, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1940, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1940, Correspondence, A-Z. (Box 18.)
  - 1941, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1941, Correspondence, A-O.
  - 1941, Correspondence, P-Z. (Box 19.)
  - 1942, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1942, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1943, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1943, Correspondence, A-J.
  - 1943, Correspondence, K-Z. (Box 20.)
  - 1944, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1944, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1945, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1945, Correspondence, A-Z. (Box 21.)
  - 1946, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1946, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1947, Correspondence, miscellaneous. (Box 22.)
  - 1947, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1948, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1948, Correspondence, A-L.
  - 1948, Correspondence, M-Z. (Box 23.)
  - 1949, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1949, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1950, Correspondence, miscellaneous. (Box 24.)
  - 1950, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1951, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1951, Correspondence, A-Z. (Box 25.)
  - 1952, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1952, Correspondence, A-M.
  - 1952, Correspondence, N-Z. (Box 26.)
  - 1953, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1953, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1954, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1954, Correspondence, A-Z. (Box 27.)
  - 1955, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1955, Correspondence, A-J.
  - 1955, Correspondence, K-Z. (Box 28.)
  - 1956, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1956, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1957, Correspondence, miscellaneous. (Box 29.)
  - 1957, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1958, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1958, Correspondence, A-J.
  - 1958, Correspondence, K-Z (Box 30.)
  - 1959, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1959, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1960, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1960, Correspondence, A-Z. (Box 31.)
  - 1961, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1961, Correspondence, A-J.
  - 1961, Correspondence, K-Z. (Box 32.)
  - 1962, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1962, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1963, Correspondence, miscellaneous. (Box 33.)
  - 1963, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1964, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1964, Correspondence, A-G.
  - 1964, Correspondence, H-Z. (Box 34.)
  - 1965, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1965, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1966, Correspondence, miscellaneous. (Box 35.)
  - 1966, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1967, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1967, Correspondence, A-H.
  - 1967, Correspondence, I-Z. (Box 36.)
  - 1968, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1968, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1969, Correspondence, miscellaneous. (Box 37.)
  - 1969, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - 1970, Correspondence, miscellaneous.
  - 1970, Correspondence, A-Z.
  - Correspondence with father (E.B. Treat), 1898-1911.
  - Correspondence with father (E.B. Treat), 1912-1921. (Box 38.)
  - Correspondence between Prof. and Mrs. Treat and Prof. and Mrs. Yamoto Ichihashi, 1942-45.
- Speeches and Writings, 1905-1968.
  - Alien Land Legislation. (Box 38.)
  - America's View of Japanese.
  - Awakened Orient.
  - Awakening of the Orient, Opportunities and Responsibilities for San Francisco and California.
  - California and the Japanese.
  - China and Japan.
  - China and Korea, 1885-1894.
  - Constitution Making in China.
  - Cosmopolitanism in California.
  - David Starr Jordan.
  - Early Japanese Foreign Relations.
  - Early Sino-Japanese Diplomatic Relations.
  - Far East.
  - Foundations of American Policy in the Far East.
  - Friendship of Japan and the United States.
  - Good Offices of the United States during the Sino-Japanese War.
  - Intellectual Bond between Japan and the United States.
  - Japan, America, and the Great War.
  - Japanese in California.
  - Japanese in Manchuria.
  - Mikado's Ratification of the Foreign Treaties.
  - National Land System,1785-1820.
  - Need of the Orient.
  - New Indian Councils.
  - New Lights of Japanese History.
  - Philippine Independence.
  - Possibilities and Facts.
  - Shanghai, January 28, 1932.
  - Stanford Anecdote.
  - Status of the Slave in the Law Courts.
  - Thomas Welton Stanford, An American Pioneer in Australia.
  - Weekly war reviews.
  - Book reviews, 1910-16, 1922-23, 1929-45. (Box 39.)
  - Classroom lectures and lecture notes.
    - History of land systems.
    - United States history, 1783-1844.
    - Bibliography and criticism.
    - History of Japan.
    - History of the Far East.
    - History of the Far East (Box 40.)
  - Clippings.
- Subject File, 1865-1973.
  - Adams, Ephraim Douglas. (Box 41.)
  - American Committee for Non-participation in Japanese Aggression.
  - American Historical Association, 1915 program.
  - Asia, clippings, 1922, 1924-25.
  - Asiatic Society of Japan.
  - Atom bomb, decision to drop on Japan.
  - Australia, clippings, 1922.
  - Bibliography.
    - Correspondence with libraries.
    - Correspondence with libraries. (Box 42.)
    - Lists.
  - Biographical file.
  - China.
    - General.
    - Canton Christian College, 1924.
    - Clippings, 1921-24.
    - Clippings, 1925-26. (Box 43.)
    - Money.
    - Industrial cooperatives.
    - Relations with Japan.
    - Relief.
    - Riots of 1925.
    - Shanghai incident of May 30, 1925.
    - Shanghai incident of 1932.
    - Shantung Province, Chinese memorandum claiming restitution of German properties.
    - United States relations, 1911-40.
    - United States relations since 1941.
    - University of China. (Box 44.)
    - Weale, Putnam, Report on a Confidential Mission to Canada, England, and the United States in 1921.
  - Chinese-Japanese studies in the United States.
  - Civil War letters.
  - Colton's Atlas of the Union (1965).
  - Far East, Clippings and maps.
  - Franklin, Benjamin.
  - Harris, Townsend. (Box 45.)
  - Henry, James M.
  - Honors and awards.
  - Hoover, Herbert C.
    - Oral history interviews with H.C. Hoover.
      - April 8, 1933.
      - August 25, 1940.
      - August 21, 1945.
    - Clippings.
  - Huston, Jay Calvin.
  - Japan.
    - General.
    - Clippings scrapbook, 1907-08.
    - Clipping scrapbook, 1919-23.
    - Clippings, 1921-26. (Box 46.)
    - Economy. (Box 47.)
    - Expedition to Formosa.
    - Manchurian question.
    - Shantung Province.
    - United States relations.
  - Japanese in California.
  - Japanese in California. (Box 48.)
  - Japanese in the United States.
  - Jordan, David Starr.
  - Korea, independence movement, 1919-20.
  - Mannix, W.F., Memoirs of Li Hung Chang.
  - Maps, miscellaneous.
  - Matsuoka, Y.
  - Memorabilia. (Box 49.)
  - Miscellaneous clippings.
  - Pearl Harbor investigation.
  - President's Commission on the Assassination of President Kennedy.
  - Reprints of published articles given to P.J. Treat by friends and colleagues. (Box 50.)
  - Sheppard, Eli T.
  - Shibusawa, Viscount E.
  - Sierra Club.
  - Sun Yat-Sen.
    - Letter (holograph, signed) by Sun Yat-Sen to President Harding, May 5, 1921, (with typed copy).
    - Letter of Alexander Baxter, Acting President of Canton Christian College, to C.K. Edmunds, President of Canton Christian College, concerning the visit of Sun Yat Sen, December 22, 1923.
    - Clippings.
  - Travel brochures for Japan and China, 1920-21.
  - Trip to the Far East, 1912.
  - Trip to the Far East, 1921-22 (Box 51.)
  - Trip, miscellaneous notes.
- Research File, 1855-1939.
  - Bailey, Leonard W., Historical Development of the Modern Chinese Navy. (Box 51.)
  - Clyde, Paul H., Attitudes and Policies of George F. Seward, American Minister at Peking, 1876-1880.
  - Kinney, Charles Bishop (South Manchuria Railway Co.), first-hand reports on the political, military, and economic situation in Manchuria, 1934-39.
  - Kinney, Henry W. (South Manchuria Railway Co.), first-hand reports on the political, military, and economic situation in Manchuria, 1927-36.
  - Longborough, William B., The Boyhood of Anson Burlingame on the Western Reserve, 1820-40.
  - Ming, Lewis, American Interest in the Far Eastern Crisis.
  - Pruyn, Robert H. (Minister to Japan).
    - Letters received relating to action in the Straits of Siminosaki against Daimio Chosu, 1864.
    - Extracts of letters from R.H. Pruyn to his wife from Japan, 1862-65. (Box 52.)
  - Pryor, Helen B., letters from medical doctors in China concerning events in Nanking during 1937-38.
  - Sheppard, Eli T. (selected copies of papers at the Library of Congress).
    - Copies of diplomatic records relating to E.T. Sheppard's activities in the U.S. Foreign Service, 1877-80.
    - Letters of Dr. S. Wells Williams, the Legation Secretary, to E.T. Sheppard, 1873-76.
    - Notes on Americans in the Far East.
    - Letters of Frederick F. Low, U.S. Minister at Peking to E.T. Sheppard, 1872-74.
    - Letters sent and received by E.T. Sheppard, 1874-76.
    - Manuscript entitled General Grant in the Orient.
  - U.S. State Department records (selected copies of diplomatic records relating to the Far East deposited at the National Archives).
    - Directions for copying documents and a list of finding aids.
    - China.
      - Rockhill's memo on the open door policy, 1899.
      - Register of instructions, 1895-1905.
      - Register of despatches, 1895-1905.
      - Despatches, instructions, etc., 1971-79.
      - Despatches, instructions, etc., 1880-85, 1894-1906. (Box 53.)
    - France.
      - Despatches, instructions, etc., 1898-1900.
    - Germany.
      - Despatches, instructions, etc., 1898-1904.
    - Great Britain.
      - Register of despatches and instructions, 1895-1905.
      - Despatches, 1898-1904.
    - Hawaii
      - Despatches, instructions, etc., 1897-98.
    - Japan. (Box 54.)
      - Consular appointments, 1859-94.
      - Report to Townsend Harris concerning the commercial treaty, 1855.
      - Treaties.
      - Miscellaneous reports of the Diplomatic Bureau.
      - Register of despatches and instructions.
      - Despatches, instructions, etc., 1865-72.
      - Despatches, instructions, etc., 1873-81. (Box 55.)
      - Despatches, instructions, etc., 1882-90. (Box 56.)
      - Despatches, instructions, etc., 1891-94. (Box 57.)
      - Despatches relating to the Anglo-Japanese Treaty of 1894.
      - Despatches, instruction, etc., 1895-99.
      - Despatches, instructions, etc., 1900-05. (Box 58.)
      - Despatches, instructions, etc., 1906. (Box 59.)
    - Korea.
      - Register of despatches and instructions, 1883-1905.
      - Despatches, instructions, etc., 1883-1905.
    - Russia.
      - Despatches, instructions, etc., 1879-1905.
- Pamphlets and Printed Matter, 1914-1923.
  - List of pamphlets and printed matter, arranged alphabetically by author or title. (Box 60.)
  - A-D.
  - E-P. (Box 61.)
  - R-Z. (Box 62.)
  - Government publications. (Box 63.)
- Increment, February, 1985
  - Mimeographed correspondence, book reviews, and ethnological studies of the Philippines, 1910-1912, by Otley C. Beyer; and a mimeog aphed transcript of a speech by D. R. Williams, 1926, relating to legal protection of Americans residing in China (Box 63.)